-==www.RagBear.com==- 是, 首相  第2季第5集
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-=破烂熊字幕组=- 翻译: 多切 校对: Tpring 时间轴: 褪色の蓝
还政于民
早安 伯纳      早安 首相
Morning.          Morning.
您要在5分钟内去电视摄影棚
You have to leave for the TV studiosin five minutes.
我准备好了
I'm ready.
您还记得访谈的内容吗?
Do you remember what the interview's about?
地方政府
Local government.
唯一一件我无处下手的事
The one thing I can do nothing about.
这些可恶的政务委员会 都由一群腐败的
These wretched councils are run by a bunch of corrupt morons
耍小聪明的白痴管理
who are too clever by half.
有小聪明就不叫白痴了
The most a moron can be is less clever by half.
这些委员不都是民主选举出来的吗?
These councillors are democratically elected.
那要看你怎么定义"民主"了
Depends how you define democracy.
只有约25%的人在地方选举时投了票
Only about 25% of people vote in a local election.
投票也只把它当成支持率调查
Those who do regard it as a popularity pole
给中央政府做参考的
for the real leaders in Westminster.
但那些地方委员也还是民意代表
But councillors are still representatives.
他们代表谁呀?
Who do they represent?
没人知道自己的委员是谁
Nobody knows who their councillor is.
你知道你的委员是谁吗?
Do you know who yours is?
不知道          你当然不会知道
No.        Well, no, of course you don't.
那些委员也都清楚
The councillors know this,
所以他们4年都胡来一气
so they spend four totally unaccountable years
拿着公款沽名钓誉
on a publicly subsidised ego trip.
他们扰乱内城区 把学校搞垮
They ruin the inner cities, let the schools fall to bits,
打击警察士气 削弱法律权威
they demoralise the police and undermine law and order,
最后就来怪我
then blame me.
您要这么说吗?          没听到我刚说了吗?
Will you say that? I've just said it. Didn't you hear me?
不 我是说在电视上
No, I mean on television.
当然不会 那样显得我没肚量
Of course not. It'd make me sound intolerant.
豪兹维斯区委员长 该死的艾格尼丝-莫豪
Houndsworth Council leader, Agnes Moorhouse,
威胁要扣留给警察的拨款
threatens to withhold police funds
并禁止他们使用政府房产
and ban them from council property.
她不能这样 1964年警务法案第5条规定
She can't do that. Section 5 of the Police Act, 1964.
"区政府必须保质保量提供警力" 上面写着
Councils must provide an adequate and efficient police force.
她说除非警员队伍有50%黑人
She says that until the police force is 50% black,
否则既不够质 也不够量
it can't be adequate or efficient.
她怎么证明          不幸的是 她治下的警察
She can't prove that.        Unfortunately, her own police force
无论质和量 在全国都排倒数第一
is the most inadequate and least efficient in the country.
大家都担心上了法庭 她能证明出来
Everybody's terrified that she will prove it.
汉弗莱 我们得对这个莫豪有所动作
Humphrey, we've got to do something about Agnes Moorhouse.
她的辖区已经完全成了禁区      的确
Her borough's practically a no go area.        Indeed.
现在怎么办?      写封措词严厉的信如何?
What?        How about a strongly worded letter?
然后收到一封措词更严厉的信
And get a more strongly worded letter in reply,
还抄送给报社? 这不是自找麻烦吗
copied to the newspapers? Asking for trouble.
拿法律对付她?          她是个律师
Draw her attention to the law.        She is a lawyer.
钻法律空子正是她的看家本领
Getting round the law is what she's paid for.
那干脆不理她?
Why not just ignore her?
让大家说我把市镇控制权拱手让给
Have everyone say I'd handed over control of the inner cities
那些激进分子吗?
to the militant loonies?
这女人是个疯子 汉弗莱
She's a wild woman, Humphrey.
不 必须得有人跟她谈谈
No, someone's got to have a word with her.
讲讲安全问题      检察官?
Point out the security implications.        A law officer?
不 不能是政治对抗 必须是行政人员
No. Can't be a political confrontation. Has to be an official.
必须是负责保安事务的人
Somebody with responsibility for security.
必须是负责...
Somebody with responsibility...
不不 首相 不行 她是个大怪兽
No, no, no, no, Prime Minister, no! She's a monster!
不不 这事归警察厅 内政部
No, i i it's up to Scotland Yard, the Home Office,
安全局...我是说特工局....军情五处
the Security Branch, er, Special Branch, I mean, the...the Ml5,
大法官 环境部...
the Lord Chancellor, Department of the Environment...
白鳕鱼管理局?      白鳕鱼...不不
The White Fish Authority?      White Fish... No, no, no!
安全部门不是你负责的吗
Don't you coordinate the security services?
是 是
Yes, yes...
或者我们该换个人来负责?
Or should we give that job to someone else?
不 不 不
No, no, no, no, no.
就这么定了 去跟她私下谈谈
That's agreed, then. A quiet word.
达成君子协议
Come to a gentlemen's agreement.
可她不是君子
But she's not a gentleman!
她连淑女都算不上
She's not even a lady!
我要你来对付她 走吧 伯纳
I want YOU to handle her. Come on.
对付她?
Handle her?
进来
Come in.
艾格尼丝-莫豪来了 汉弗莱爵士          好吧
Agnes Moorhouse to see you, Sir Humphrey.        Right.
亲爱的女士 见到你真高兴
Oh, my dear lady, how very nice to meet you.
请进 坐这边好吗?
Come in. Won't you come and sit down? Now...
好吧 能不能帮莫豪小姐倒杯茶?
Um... right... Would you get Miss Moorhouse a cup of tea.
或者是莫豪夫人?
Or is it Mrs Moorhouse?
你很关心我的婚姻状况吗?          不不
Is my marital status really your concern?        Er, no, no.
只是...你知道
It's just... You know,
我只是担心 呃...
I was just... worried about whether the... er...
呃 你能...帮她倒杯茶吗?
Er, would you get... her a cup of tea?
我该怎么称呼你呢 莫豪小姐吗
What should I call you? Ms Moorhouse?
叫我艾格尼丝 我该怎么叫你
Call me Agnes. What shall I call you?
你可以叫我汉弗莱爵士
...well, you can call me Sir Humphrey.
那么 亲爱的女士
Now, my dear lady...
我不是你"亲爱的女士"
I'm not your "dear lady".
少来这套伪绅士的废话了 好吗?
Don't patronise me and cut out the sexist crap, OK?
好吧 艾格尼丝
Er... OK, Agnes.
我约你见面是觉得 我们该交流一下
I wanted us to have this meeting so we could try
促进共识
and understand one another.
这当然是不谋而合的          是吗?
I'm sure we're in agreement.        Really?
显然 你对治理国家有自己的一套
You have your own views about how Britain should be run,
但我相信我们俩都同意 根本上要
but I'm sure we agree on a fundamental basis
保证秩序和政府权威
of order and authority.
说对一半      一半?
That's half true.      Half true?
你同意 我不同意          可这很明显啊
You agree, I don't.        But it's obvious!
很明显 你用现行体制立了法
if you've got it made under this system,
是想用政府权威维护你的特权
you use authority to preserve your privileges.
可那些流浪汉 失业者和穷人呢?
What about the homeless, the unemployed, the poor?
艾格尼丝 我了解他们
I know all about them.
真的 你了解什么?
Really? What do you know?
我看过所有发表的报告
I've read all the published papers.
所有统计数据 所有官方汇报
I've seen all the statistics.
相信我 亲爱的女士...艾格尼丝 我...
Believe me, dear lady... Agnes, I... I...
我真的了解他们      好呀
I do know all about them.      Fine.
半磅黄油要多少钱?
What does half a pound of margarine cost?
什么?      半磅黄油要多少钱?
What?       What does half a pound of margarine cost?
呃 我怎么知道...2毛
Oh... er... How should I know? Er... 20p.
2毛?      2块4吧 我不知道
20p?!      2.40! I don't know!
就是 你怎么会知道?
Right. Why should you?
社保局几点开门呢?
What time do Social Security offices open?
一台单杠式取暖器
How long can you run a one bar fire
5毛钱可以跳多少表?
with 50 pence in the meter?
我不太明白你在说什么
I'm not entirely sure I follow.
你当然不知道 如果你知道
If you knew that,
你就不会同意用政府来支撑制度
you wouldn't agree about using authority to support the system.
我能理解 我也同情 帮人脱贫功德无量啊
I do understand. I do sympathise.
但我们真的没有资源来实现
But we haven't the resources to achieve that.
谁没有?
Who hasn't?
国家      真的吗?
The nation.        Really?
这张桌子是国家的吗? 这件陶瓷?
Does this desk belong to the nation? This china?
是白瓷      白瓷
Porcelain.      Porcelain.
这些画是国家的? 要么是你私人的?
These portraits? Or are they your own?
这些是政府财产
They're government property.
很好 这些东西可以卖...差不多8万吧?
Oh, good. They should fetch about   what?   80,000.
足够20个单亲家庭过1年了
That'll keep 20 one parent families for a year.
你的工资呢?
What about your salary?
这与此无关
That has nothing to do with it!
很好 也一起划过来
Good, then we'll have that, too.
给你每周100元 又给需要的人每年省出7万
Leave you ?00 a week. That's 70,000 a year for the needy.
我的工资是经济综合结构的一部分
My salary is merely part of a complex economic structure.
好呀 我们把它简单化
We'll simplify it.
毕竟 你也不是为了发财
After all, you don't want to make a profit
才为国效力的 对吧?
out of serving your country, do you?
啊 茶来了
Ah, tea.
这边 艾琳
Over here, Eileen. Um...
太好了 非常感谢 要我做东道吗?
How very nice. Thank you so much. Shall I be mother?
告诉我 艾格尼丝
Tell me, um... Agnes...
你有一条政策 你辖区内只允许出售
...this policy of yours of only allowing free range eggs
放养鸡下的蛋 这能改善贫困吗?
to be sold in your borough, how does this help poverty?
动物也有权利 懂吗
Animals have rights too, you know.
圈养鸡一辈子生不如死
A battery chicken's life isn't worth living.
你愿意一辈子跟600名
Would you want to spend your life packed in
吵吵闹闹 臭烘烘的生灵挤在一起吗?
with 600 other squawking, smelly creatures,
无法呼吸新鲜空气 无法移动
unable to breathe fresh air, unable to move,
无法伸展 无法思考?
unable to think?
当然不愿意
Certainly not.
所以我从不参选议员
That's why I never stood for Parliament.
要糖吗?      不用 谢谢
Sugar?        No, thank you.
好 谈谈警察问题吧
Now, let's turn to this matter of the police.
你想要扣留警察的拨款
You want to withhold funds from the police,
禁止他们使用政府房产
ban them from council property,
解雇警察局长 再设立一些禁区
sack the Chief Constable, and allow several no go areas.
没错        但你难道不明白
That's it.        But can't you see
充足的警力对我们大家都有好处?
that an adequate police enforcement is in all our interests?
尤其能照顾到那些贫困的
And it is especially in the interestsof all those poor,
住在高犯罪率区域的平民
ordinary folk who dwell in the high crime housing estates.
恕难苟同
I don't accept that.
你想让他们处在被抢劫 强奸
Oh, you want them to be in danger of being mugged
被土炸弹炸死的危险当中吗
and raped and bombed?
这是没有办法的事
Can't be helped.
可这会最终颠覆
But this could lead to the overthrow
我们的政府体制 我们的整个生活方式
of our system of government, our way of life!
是你的 不是他们的
Yours, not theirs.
那么 你乐意把议会废除掉?        是的
You would be happy to abolish Parliament?      Yes.
还有法院?        是的
The courts?      Yes.
君主制呢?        当然了
The monarchy?!      Of course.
既然你在兴头上 还想烧了我的办公室吧
Perhaps you'd like to burn down my office!
火柴在这里
That matches are over here!
不 当然不想了         为什么?
No, certainly not.          Why?
也许我用得上
I may need it.
你知道那个女人艾格尼斯-莫豪吗?        怎么?
You know that Agnes Moorhouse woman?        Yes?
我让汉弗莱去找她谈谈
I told Humphrey to have a word with her.
有趣的尝试
Interesting experiment.
他说谈得不错 但又不愿多说
He says it went well, but he didn't want to talk about it
只在10分钟里干掉了4大杯威士忌
and had four whiskies in ten minutes.
这些地方政府怎么回事?
What is it about local government?
我刚跟市政厅闹了一场
I've had trouble with the town hall.
他们把老年人圣诞派对取消了
They've cancelled the old people's Christmas party.
为什么?        跟新员工加班协议有关
Why?          New staff overtime agreements.
"都是你丈夫的错 哈克夫人"
"It's your husband's fault.
"你让他给我们钱"
Tell him to give us the money"
"就让你们开派对"
"and you can have the party."
好呀 全国所有市政厅的所有蠢事
Every piece of stupidity and incompetence
和不作为行为都怪在我身上
in every town hall in Britain is blamed on me.
准是多萝西
That'll be Dorothy.
我叫她过来谈谈这件事
I asked her up here to have a word about that very thing.
多萝西 进来吧
Dorothy, come in.
过来坐吧
Come and sit down.
你告诉我 地方政府到底什么毛病?
Now, tell me, what is wrong with local government?
嗯 这是种非敌既我的状况
Well, it's a them and us situation.
地方执政者应该是我们
The local authority ought to be us.
我们人民 还是我们中央政府?
Us the people or us the government?
在民主制度下 应该是一样的啊
In a democracy that ought to be the same thing.
我们都知道不是的
We all know it isn't.
不 我是说我们人民
I mean us, the people.
应该服务我们 是我们一份子 可他们不是
They ought to be running things for us.
只为他们自己做事
But they're running things for them.
为他们的权力 便利和利益
For their power, their convenience and their benefit.
这我知道        那该怎么办
I know that.          So what's the answer?
对抗他们        不 让他们变成我们
Fight them.        No. Make them us.
怎么说?
How do you mean?
假设你要阻止一个大型政府项目 你怎么办?
How do you stop a major government project?
找公务员配合
Join the Civil Service.
不 我是说如果你是个普通人
If you're an ordinary person.
我不记得当平民是什么感觉了
I can't remember what that was like.
照民意测验来看 你就快知道了
Judging from opinion polls, you'll soon find out.
想象你是个平头百姓 吉姆
Just imagine you're an ordinary person, Jim.
好 我试试
Well, I'll try.
假设要扩宽道路 或者建机场
Imagine you want to stop a road widening scheme
要拆迁你的房子 你会怎么办?
or an airport being built. What do you do?
给你的议会代表写信        这有用吗?
Write to your MP.        That does the trick?
当然没用 可普通人就是这么做的
Of course not, but that's what ordinary people do
因为普通人都是笨蛋
'cause ordinary people are stupid.
这就是为什么他们选你吧?
Is that why they elected you?
别拆我台 亲爱的 谢谢
Stop barracking, darling, please.
我正试着理解多萝西的见解呢
I'm trying to understand what Dorothy's driving at.
普通人会组成一个组织
Ordinary people form a group
来与不利的官方计划对抗
to fight official plans they don't want
由这个组织代表所有当地人
and this group represents the local people.
它跟地方政府不一样
This group is different from the local authority
因为地方政府并不代表
because the local authority doesn't really represent
当地人民        为什么?
the local people.          Why not?
因为政务委员都是地方小团体人士
Councillors are all drawn from tiny local parties.
当一个社区真的重视某个问题
When a local community really cares about an issue,
他们组成一个委员会 然后上街
they form a committee, and then they talk to people
去超市 或挨家挨户游说
in the supermarkets and on the doorstep.
争取支持 争取资金
They drum up support and raise money.
而这些钱跟政府收费不同
And this money isn't like the rates.
它们会被用在人们希望用的地方
It's spent on what people actually want it spent on.
我打赌本地的百姓都乐意
I bet ordinary people would like
让老年人开个圣诞派对
the old folks to have a Christmas party.
当然 可市政厅宁愿要幢新大楼
The town hall would rather have a new town hall
或者让委员们去巴哈马岛公费考察
or a councillors' fact finding mission to the Bahamas.
那该怎么办?      很明显呀 废除他们
What do you do?        It's obvious. Abolish them.
把权力都揽到中央政府
Invest all power in the central government.
这正是汉弗莱的主张        是吧 什么?
That's exactly what Humphrey would say.        See? What?
吉姆 你完全没领会
Jim, you've completely missed the point
我说的意思啊
of everything I've been saying.
我的意思是要还政于民
The idea is to return power to ordinary people
而不让市政机器霸占
and take it away from the town hall machine.
使得地方政府真正负起责任来
Make local government genuinely accountable.
对 可怎么做?
Yes, but how?
本月上有篇文章规划好了
It's all in an article in this month's "Political Review"
作者叫马里奥教授
by Professor Marriott.
办法是 多多设立小选区
Now, you create little voting districts.
每200户人家选出
200 or so households electing
自己的行政委员会 化城为村
their own little parish council, a city village.
这个行政委员会的主席
The chairman of this little parish council
就是他们在地方政府中的代表
is their representative on the local authority.
那每个镇区就有500个委员了
You'd have about 500 councillors to each borough.
没错 然后他们再选出个执行委员会
That's right. So they'd elect an executive council.
这样地方政府就有了议会和内阁
The local authority would have a parliament and a cabinet.
不能让议会选内阁 不能这样
Parliament don't elect the Cabinet. We don't want that.
这样参与性就强过头了
That'd be taking participation to extreme lengths.
这些委员会就这样
These councils would.
每一个议员就能与他左邻右舍
Each councillor would be in door to door contact
选他的人保持紧密联系
with the people who voted for him.
多萝西 这简直是1832年议会改革法案
Dorothy, this could be like the Great Reform Act of 1832.
这些委员会就像当年的不平等选区
These councils are like old rotten boroughs.
六七个人就可以决定
Half a dozen people deciding
未来4年市政厅的领导
who'll be in the town hall for the next four years.
没错        而伟大的改革家就是我
Precisely.      And I shall be the great reformer!
应该由我亲自颁布
Hacker's Reform Bill. I shall introduce it myself.
这个国家的权力不出自
The power of this country does not lie in
办公室和机关 它出自每个英国子民
offices and institutions, it lies in the stout hearts
坚强的意志和心灵之中
and strong wills of the yeomen of Britain!
女人也投票啊
Women have the vote, too!
还有英国女子民
The yeowomen of Britain.
平民 平头百姓? 不行
Yeopersons. Yeopeople? No.
这个岛国的人民
...the people of this island race.
他们宽厚而睿智的肩膀...
On their broad and wise shoulders...
肩膀怎么能睿智呢
You can't have wise shoulders.
他们宽厚的肩膀和睿智的心灵...头脑
On their broad shoulders and wise hearts... heads...
我们的未来 蕴藏在他们睿智的头脑中
In their wise heads lies our destiny.
我们必须还政于民
We must give back power to the people!
我应当亲自颁布这个...
And I shall be the one to introduce this... um...
这个新计划取什么名呢?
What shall I call this new scheme?
民主?
Democracy?
请进
YES
汉弗莱爵士 您找我?        是的 伯纳
You wanted to see me?        Oh, yes, Bernard.
伯纳 我想跟你谈谈
Bernard, I want to have a word with you
马里奥教授的文章
about Professor Marriott's article.
对 我觉得地方政府是该改革了
I think it's time we reformed local government.
是吗 伯纳?
Do you?
是的
Yes.
至少 我觉得我同意
At least I think I did.
就是说 我并不是太反对
That is, I'm not wholly against it.
尽管也有很多...有力的
Although there are many... convincing,
有人认为很有见地的反对意见
some might say conclusive, arguments against it.
确实是有人 伯纳
Some might indeed, Bernard.
对 为什么
Yes. Why?
伯纳 因为一旦你开创了
Because once you create
真正民主的地方社区 就不会到此为止
genuinely democratic local communities, it won't stop there.
不会吗?      当然不会
Won't it?      Well, of course it won't.
你想想 这些机构一旦成立
You see, once they get established,
他们必将争取更大权力
they'll insist on more power.
政治家们将不敢不放权
Politicians will be too frightened to withhold them,
于是就形成了地区小政府
so you'll get regional government.
这有问题吗?      伯纳 过来坐下
Would that matter?      Bernard, come and sit down.
伯纳 假设今时今日
What happens at the moment if there is
在诺丁汉有了一块空地
some vacant land in, say, Nottingham
有几个方案争着要用它
and there are rival proposals for its use
要建医院 学校或机场呢?
hospital, college, airport?
我们设一个部门联席委员会
We set up an inter departmental committee.
卫生部 教育部 交通部 环境部
Health, Education, Transport, Environment.
要求他们打报告 开些会 交提案
Ask for papers, hold meetings, propose,
讨论 修正 再打报告 重拟提案
discuss, revise, report back, re draft.
非常正确 数个月卓有成效的工作
Precisely. Months of fruitful work.
最终达成一个成熟且负责任的结论
Leading to a mature and responsible conclusion.
但如果有个地区政府
But if you have regional government,
他们在诺丁汉就可以决定
they decide it all in Nottingham!
也许开几个会就完了 相当地不专业
Probably in a couple of meetings! Complete amateurs!
可那是他们的地区        那我们怎么办?
It is their city.        And what happens to us?
工作量大幅减少
Well, much less work.
对 工作量大幅减少
Yes, much less work!
少到几个大臣自己就能完成了
So little that ministers might be able to do it on their own,
我们会失去很多的权力
so we'd have much less power!
我不确定我想不想要权力
I don't know if I want power.
伯纳德 如果该掌权的人不掌权
If the right people don't have power,
你知道会怎样吗?
know what happens?
不该掌的人就掌权了
The wrong people get it!
政客们 委员们 普通选民们
Politicians, councillors, ordinary voters!
但在民主制度下 这不是天经地义吗?
But aren't they supposed to in a democracy?
我们是英式民主 伯纳          这怎么说?
This is a British democracy, Bernard!        How do you mean?
英式民主认为 我们需要有个体制
British democracy recognises that you need a system
保护生活中重要的东西
to protect the important things of life
保证它们不落到化外之民手上
and keep them out of the hands of the barbarians!
比如说歌剧
Things like the opera...
BBC广播3台
...Radio 3...
英国乡间 法律
...the countryside... the law...
还有大学
...the universities.
两所都算 (牛津和剑桥)
Both of them.
而我们就是这个体制         天啊
And we are that system.        Gosh!
我们运作一个文明的 贵族的政府机器
We run a civilised, aristocratic government machine
偶尔由普选调节一下
tempered by occasional general elections.
从1832年议会改革起 我们已经逐渐
Since 1832, we have been gradually
将普通选民排除出政府系统
excluding the voter from government.
现在我们已经达到了
Now we've got them to a point
只让他们每5年选举一次的地步
where they just vote once every five years
还是有些小丑利用这个途径
for which buffoons will try to
干涉我们的政策
interfere with OUR policies
而你倒很乐意把这一切都抛弃?
and you are happy to see all that thrown away?
不不 我不是说...
Well, no, no, I didn't mean...
伯纳 你愿意看到湖区
Bernard, do you want the Lake District
变成一大片房车营地吗?
turned into a gigantic caravan site?
皇家歌剧院变成赌场大厅呢?
The Royal Opera House into a bingo hall?
国家剧院变成地毯超市呢?
The National Theatre into a carpet sale warehouse?
其实看上去挺像的
Well, it looks like one, actually.
我们给设计师封了爵士
We gave the architect a knighthood
就是为了不让人这么说
so that nobody would ever say that.
你愿意广播3台全天播流行音乐吗?
Do you want Radio 3 to broadcast pop music 24 hours a day?
要是他们把电视上
How would you feel
所有文化节目都取消 你什么感觉?
if they took all the culture programmes off television?
我不知道 我从来不看
I never watch them.
我也不看 但它们的存在至关重要
Neither do I, but it's vital to know they're there!
可您说地方政府腐败无能的
You said local government was corrupt and incompetent.
确实如此 伯纳
So it is, Bernard.
已经腐败无能到连大臣们都看出来了
So corrupt and incompetent that even ministers recognise it.
这就意味着它们集中了
Which means that they centralise.
所有的实务都交给了我们
They give all the responsible jobs to us.
我们是...政府之中的花朵 伯纳
We... are the flower of government, Bernard.
地方政府尽管是粪土堆
Local government may be a dunghill...
但它们能培育出美丽的玫瑰
...but it grows beautiful roses.
您是说...
You mean...
是的 没错 伯纳
Yes, that's right, Bernard.
但如果我们试着清除粪土堆
But if we try to clean up the dunghill
不小心失去了平衡
and... lose our balance...
我们就要摔在...      谢谢 伯纳
We land in the...      Thank you, Bernard.
有劳你了 谢谢
That's very good of you. Thank you.
你可以理解我的担忧吧 阿诺德
So you see why I'm so worried, Arnold.
这个马里奥计划是个导火索
This Marriott scheme is the thin end of the wedge.
它最终会侵蚀到公务员系统
It could eventually undermine the Civil Service.
我不觉得有那么危险
Oh, I don't think there's any danger of that.
你运用得法就不会
Not if you play it right.
哈克只是在抓救命稻草
Hacker's just grasping at straws.
这是个古老的逻辑悖论
It's the old logical fallacy.
猫都有4条腿 我的狗也有4条腿
All cats have four legs. My dog has four legs...
因此我的狗是只猫
Therefore my dog is a cat.
政客逻辑害了他
He's suffering from politician's logic.
必须做实事 这是实事 因此必须做
Something must be done therefore we must do it.
可如果做错了 还不如不做
But doing the wrong thing is worse than doing nothing.
做什么都不如什么都不做
Doing anything is worse than doing nothing.
对 毕竟 唯一一件能让政治家
After all, what is the one thing that obsesses
追求一生的是什么?
politicians throughout their careers?
很显然是曝光度和支持率
Well, obviously publicity and popularity.
报纸上登个名 电视上露个脸
Name in the paper, face on the telly.
任何能帮他们赢得选举的东西      很对
Anything to help get them re elected.        Quite.
执政党意味着名声 荣耀 显赫
Government is fame and glory and importance
还有超大办公室和司机
and big offices and chauffeurs
还有特里-沃根的专访
and being interviewed by Terry Wogan.
而在野党则是无足轻重 无关紧要的
Opposition is impotence and insignificance
别人都问你是不是认识罗宾-戴
and people at parties asking you if you know Robin Day.
但是 阿诺德 公务员体系改革
But, Arnold, reforming the Civil Service
也许能为他们赢得民心
might win them popularity.
但这是不可能的 是吧 汉弗莱?
But it can't ever happen... can it, Humphrey?
怎么不能 阿诺德?         这跟地方政府是一样的
Why not, Arnold?      It's the same as in local government.
6万人的大选区
Constituencies of 60,000 are
选民注定无法了解他们的议会代表
far too big for people to know their MP.
选民们作出决定的基础是
Electors make up their minds on the basis
广播电视和媒体的宣传
of the telly and the radio and the press.
是的 他们选出他们最喜欢的党派领袖
Yes, they pick their favourite party leader,
就等于投票给那党派中
then they vote for whatever clown
一小撮人指定的
a few people in their party
随便什么下三滥候选人
have chosen as their candidate.
相信我 我了解这个体制 阿诺德
I do understand how the system works, Arnold.
但你真的了解吗?
But do you?
汉弗莱 如果一个政客的生死
Listen, Humphrey, if a politician lives or dies
由他的媒体形象决定
by his media image,
那他的生存就取决于公务员公关系统
then his survival depends on the Civil Service publicity machine
来润色他愚蠢的讲话稿
helping him with his fatuous speeches
写的文章 还有媒体出镜
and articles and photo opportunities.
政客们完全依靠我们
Politicians are dependent on us.
上千名新闻官员 鼓吹他们那点小政绩
A thousand press officers to publicise their little triumphs.
掩盖他们每天的丑闻
The Official Secrets Act to conceal their daily disasters.
那么你是说 按马里奥教授的计划
So what you're saying is that under Professor Marriott's scheme,
议员会凭他们在地方上的声望当选
MPs would be elected on their local reputation
而不是党派领袖的媒体形象
rather than on their leader's media image.
对 政府和大臣们就得去挣选票
Yes, governments and ministers would have to earn their votes.
真的做选民们希望的事
Actually do what the electors want
而不是让我们按我们的方法做事
instead of leaving us to do it our way
他们只管树立形象就成
while they do the fame and glory bit.
想想都可怕
Frightening thought.
对我们可怕 但对首相呢?
Frightening to us, but what about the Prime Minister?
自然是更可怕了
Of course. Even more frightening.
公务员改革就等于撤除了
Reforming the Civil Service would remove
他的生命线
his life support system.
等于抽掉他一路爬上来的梯子
It would kick away the ladder that's put him where he is.
而且他还站在上面呢
While he's still standing on it.
非常正确
That's right.
改革公务员系统的唯一方法
The only way to reform the Civil Service system
就是把政治体制一起改掉
is to reform the political system.
没有哪个政府会改掉
No government's going to reform
赋与其权力的体制吧
the system that put it into power.
问题是 要让首相也看到危险
The thing is to get the Prime Minister to see the danger.
这是你的事
That's your job.
有了
I know.
我跟他说 这会是他最有魄力的举措
I'll tell him it'll be the most courageous thing he's ever done.
这招百发百中
That always does the trick.
进来
Yes?
艾格尼丝-莫豪来了 汉弗莱爵士
Agnes Moorhouse, Sir Humphrey.
艾格尼丝
Ah, Agnes.
请这边坐
Why don't you sit over here?
艾格尼丝 首相非常担忧
Agnes, the Prime Minister's really worried about
你对警察队伍的态度
your attitude to the police.
哦 很好
Oh, good.
因此 他计划全盘改造地方政府
So he's proposing a wholesale reform of local government.
街道代表 每200户选一个
Street representatives, voting communities of 200 households,
让他们全面参与自制市镇
total involvement of the borough electorate
总代表候选人的提名
in the selection of candidates.
不是真的吧?          恐怕是的
This isn't serious?        Oh, I'm afraid it is.
这会重创我们的民主社会改革啊
This strikes at the heart of our democratic social reforms.
你是说 人们其实不喜欢你的政策?
Do you mean the people don't want your policies?
他们要是能理解 当然会喜欢
Of course they would if they could understand,
可普通选民都头脑简单
but the ordinary voters are simple people.
他们看不到自己的需求
They don't see their needs.
他们不会分析问题
They can't analyse problems.
他们得跟着领袖 才能往该走的方向走
They need leadership to guide them the way they ought to go.
你觉得"人民"不会投票给这种领袖?
And don't you think "the people" would vote for such leadership?
人民并不总能分清好歹
People don't always understand what's good for them.
哦 我太同意你了
Oh... I do so agree with you.
是吗?      当然了
Do you?      Of course!
这就是公务员系统传承几个世纪的原因
That's how the Civil Service has survived for centuries.
我们造就了这个国家
We made this country what it is,
可没人会投票给我们
but nobody would ever vote for us!
我们清楚什么对国家有好处
We know what's right for this country!
可不是吗
So do we!
唯一办法就是 只选一小群领导人
The only way is to have a small group in charge
让人民隔几年投一次票
and let the people have a vote every few years.
如果他们对候选人了解太深
If they knew the people they were voting for...
如果让他们说上话
If they actually talked to them,
他们都会迷上那些老一套的蠢办法
they'd fall for all the silly conventional ideas!
汉弗莱           艾格尼丝?
Humphrey...        Agnes?
这对你也是个灾难 你知道吗?
This would be a disaster for you, too. you know?
我知道
I know.
社区委员会最终会形成地区政府
Community councils always lead to regional government.
艾格尼丝 我们必须阻止首相
Agnes... we must stop the Prime Minister!
你也想阻止他?
You want to stop him, too?
当然 而你得帮我
Of course. And you must help me.
怎么帮?           我想我知道要怎么做
How?        Well, I think I know how to do it.
但我要你书面保证
But I want your written assurance
不再骚扰你的地方警察局
that you will stop harassing your local police.
我是说 不再让他们民主地对你负责
I mean, stop making them democratically accountable to you.
这可以把事态缓和一下
It will remove some of the urgency.
好的 你要我怎么说?
Right. What do you want me to say?
这个 我觉得
Well, I thought...
就像这些之类
it might go something like this.
哦 汉弗莱
Oh, Humphrey...
你不参加激进运动真让人痛心
...you're a great loss to the militant revolution.
而你 亲爱的艾格尼丝
And you, my dear Agnes...
不加入公务员也让人痛心
...are a great loss to the Civil Service.
为什么汉弗莱要我亲自见见马里奥?
Why does Humphrey want me to see Marriott?
他肯定有见不得人的计划
He must have an ulterior motive.
为什么?
Why?
汉弗莱所有计划都见不得人
All Humphrey's motives are ulterior.
是吗 伯纳?
Has he, Bernard?
汉弗莱对这计划到底什么看法?
What does Humphrey really think about this plan?
这个 呃 我想...
Well, er... Well, I think...
我肯定 如果您真的决心...
That is, I'm sure, if it's what you want...
我相信汉弗莱爵士一定会...
I'm sure Sir Humphrey would...
一定会...           有这么糟?
He would... er...        As bad as that?
首相 马里奥教授来了
Professor Marriott is outside.
您要见他吗?
Will you see him?
好 当然了
Yes, of course.
伯纳 能不能请你...
Bernard, I wonder if you'd be kind enough.
汉弗莱 你对马里奥的计划有何看法?
What's your view of the Marriott plan?
我觉得 它能顺利把真正的民主
It is a brilliant way of bringing real democracy
引入英国政府
into the government of Britain.
所以你支持?        他没这么说
So you're in favour?        That's not what he said.
首相 如果你想要一个真正民主的政府
If you want real democratic government,
我定当鼎力支持
you will have my unquestioning support.
马里奥教授来了
Professor Marriott.
教授 请进 多谢光临 请坐
Professor, come in. Good of you to come. Do sit down.
首相 见到您太荣幸了
What an honour to meet you.
对 我知道
Yes, I know.
首相 马里奥教授又写了篇续作
Professor Marriott has a sequel to his original article
将要在下月出版
that's due to be published next month.
比原作还要激动人心
It is even more exciting than the first one.
跟我说说吧 教授
Tell me more, Professor.
是呀 跟首相说说它对议会的好处
Tell the PM about the benefits to Parliament.
如您所知 按照我的地方政府方案
Well, as you know, under my local government scheme,
每个市镇有500名街道代表
each borough would have its 500 street representatives.
这意味着当地议员可以
This means the local MP would be
在一个大厅里同他们交流
able to talk to them all in one hall.
让他们了解他
They'd get to know him.
正是 然后回去讲给左邻右舍听
And tell all the people in their street about him.
面对面 树立口碑
Word of mouth recommendation.
听起来真好
Sounds terrific.
等等 那参选党派起什么作用?
Where would the constituency party come in?
这就是妙处所在
Ah, that's the marvellous thing.
党派完全成了摆设了
Party organisations would be completely bypassed.
议员们将真正独立出来      什么?
MPs would become genuinely independent.        What?
如果候选人被所有委员会代表
If they were known to all their constituents
所有选民所了解
or their committee representatives,
赢得选举将不再取决于
then getting re elected would be nothing to do with
党派是否支持他们
whether the party backed them or not
而取决于选民觉得他干得怎样
but on whether the constituents felt they were doing a good job.
所以 如果议员们不再依赖党派
If the MP wasn't dependent on his party machine,
他就尽可以投票反对自己党派的政策
he could vote against his own party and get away with it.
候选人不再由官方指定
There'd be no official candidates.
选举结果完全取决于候选人的名声
Election would depend on an MP's reputation,
而不是党派领袖的形象
not the image of the party leader.
政党机器就完了 组织秘书也完了
An end of the party machine. An end to the power of the whips.
那政府要怎样让它
How would the government gets
不受欢迎的法案顺利通过呢?
its unpopular legislation through without twisting the odd arm?
少数怎样指使多数?        不行
How would it command a majority?        It couldn't.
一项法案要通过
There could only be legislation
得有多数议员支持才行
if a majority of the MPs were actually in favour of it.
议会将真正民主起来
Parliament would become genuinely democratic.
首相 这是您所提议过的
Prime Minister, it is the most courageous policy
最有魄力的方案
you have ever proposed.
教授 非常感谢 太妙了 再见
Professor, thank you so much. Fascinating. Goodbye.
谢谢您 首相
Thank you, Prime Minister.
首相 真宏伟的计划啊
Prime Minister, it's a splendid idea.
真正的民主      多萝西 这根本不能考虑
Real democracy.        It's out of the question.
马里奥的计划应该是我们
The Marriott scheme was our way
用来控制地方政府的
of controlling the local authority.
现在怎么对付莫豪的警察问题?
What will we do about Agnes Moorhouse?
首相 我又跟她谈了一次
I've had another word with her.
简而言之 首相
To put it simply, Prime Minister,
我们进行了一番非正式讨论
certain informal discussions took place
全面而坦率地交换了意见
involving a full and frank exchange of views,
从而提出了一系列计划
out of which there arose a series of proposals
最终引导了多种可行的研究目标
which proved to indicate certain promising lines of inquiry,
依此推进之后
which, when pursued,
得出结论 有某些其它方案
led to the realisation that the alternative courses of action
也许在某种情况下
might, in fact, in certain circumstances,
能对既定方针作出谨慎补充
be susceptible of discreet modification,
以实现求同存异
leading to a reappraisal of the areas of difference
寻找一条途径 使双方有条件
and pointing the way to encouraging possibilities
妥协接受并通力合作
of compromise and cooperation
如果双方都能贯彻执行
which, if bilaterally implemented
并同时作出适当的让步
with appropriate give and take on both sides,
若形势许可 也许会
might, if the climate were right,
最终创造出可能条件
have a possibility, at the end of the day,
无论过程正确与否 都能达成
of leading, rightly or wrongly,
双方均满意的解决方案
to a mutually satisfactory resolution.
你在扯什么啊?
What the hell are you talking about?
我们做了笔交易
We did a deal.
果不其然
Oddly enough,
她对民主的欲望并不比您强
she didn't seem to like the idea of democracy any more than you.
或者你     非常对 亲爱的女士
Or you.        Quite so, dear lady.
我想我们都同意
Well, I think we're all agreed
国家还没准备好
that the nation isn't quite ready for
迎接完全的民主
total democracy.
也许要到...下个世纪?
Perhaps... er... next century?
可能下个世纪 您还是首相
Well, you could still be Prime Minister next century.
那就下下世纪      是 首相
Well, the one after that.        Yes, Prime Minister.
-==www.RagBear.com==- 破烂熊字幕组 祝大家新春快乐